{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "Susan Reverby exposed one of these events that Francis Collins called a “dark chapter in history;” Barack Obama apologized for that event of this type to A´lvaro Colom, President of Guatemala. Eunice Rivers organized another of these events, whose victims included Herman Shaw and other men who were told they had “bad blood.” Either a placebo or penicillin was given to the infected subjects of, for ten points, what type of experiment that was conducted at Tuskegee University, in which African-American men were unknowingly given a sexually transmitted disease?",
      "answer": "syphilis experiments ”experiment” not needed after mentioned"
    },
    {
      "question": "The cut-stone Hall of Audience was commissioned by this ruler, who ascended to the throne after his predecessor disappeared on a voyage to explore the limits of the Atlantic Ocean. This ruler invited Ali Kolon to his court after conquering his homeland with the help of his general, Sagmandia. Andalusian architects were hired by this man to build the Djinguereber [jin-guh-rey-ber] Mosque in Timbuktu. For ten points, name this ruler of Mali who ruined economies with highly generous spending during his 1324 hajj to Mecca.",
      "answer": "Mansa Musa"
    },
    {
      "question": "This building was commissioned by William Reynolds after the Dreamland fire at Coney Island. A request from Texaco executives for an exclusive restaurant led to the creation of this building’s Cloud Club. This building’s exterior displays gargoyles and a recognizable terraced crown. Upon its completion in 1931, this William van Alen-designed building stood taller than the Empire State Building. For ten points, name this Manhattan skyscraper of the Art Deco style whose construction was funded by an American car manufacturer.",
      "answer": "Chrysler Building"
    },
    {
      "question": "This city’s community of Lenasia is historically home to its Indian population, and its Carlton Centre is the tallest skyscraper on its continent. This city was established following the discovery of gold along the Witwatersrand. A formerly-separate suburb of this city is home to Orlando Stadium, which black students marched to in a 1976 protest against the mandatory teaching of Afrikaans. Soweto Township is now part of, for ten points, what city, the most populous in South Africa?",
      "answer": "Johannesburg"
    },
    {
      "question": "These figures were alleged to have been able to walk on water with a type of wooden shoe called the “water spider.” One of these figures replicated the enemy’s crest on the lanterns of his troops to gain entrance into that enemy’s army. A famous person of this type nicknamed “Devil” led his lord to safety through Iga province. Hattori Hanzo was a member of this profession, also known as shinobi, who served Tokugawa Ieyasu. For ten points, name these stealthy mercenaries from feudal Japan.",
      "answer": [
        "ninja",
        "shinobi before mentioned"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "A bombardment before this battle was halted by Samuel Graves when the Lively’s guns woke him up from his sleep. In this battle, William Prescott withdrew his men to Cambridge after running out of ammunition. General Thomas Gage was dismissed after this battle, in which Israel Putnam allegedly ordered his militia to not fire “until you see the whites of their eyes.” For ten points, name this early battle of the Revolutionary War that predominantly took place on Breed’s Hill.",
      "answer": [
        "Battle of Bunker Hill",
        "Battle of Breed’s Hill before mentioned"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "In a quadrennial festival celebrating this deity, the peplos robe was setup like a ship’s sail on a parade cart, while the kanephoroi carried sacred baskets alongside. One epithet of this deity, Glaukopis, refers to silvery eyes and was later translated as “gray-eyed.” Tetradrachm coins featured this goddess’s face on one side and the owl, a prominent symbol of her wisdom, on the other. The Parthenon was dedicated to and named for, for ten points, what ancient Greek goddess, the virgin patron deity of Athens?",
      "answer": "Athena"
    },
    {
      "question": "During World War II, the United Kingdom invaded this modern day country as part of Operation Fork. This country experienced the “mist hardships” after the eruption of the Laki fissure. Thingvellir was the site of this country’s legislative assembly, the Althing, for over a millennia. This country’s Prime Minister, Sigmundr David, resigned in 2016 after it was discovered that he had set up a company in the Virgin Islands to avoid tax payments. For ten points, name this European island country with capital Reykjavik.",
      "answer": "Iceland"
    },
    {
      "question": "One depiction of this man shows him walking in front of mountains and clouds en route to a miners strike in Anyuan. He promoted socialist realism and artwork that was “red, light and bright” during his tenure. This man wears blue eyeshadow and rouge in a silkscreen print by Andy Warhol, and his official portrait by Ge Xiaoguang hangs on Tienanmen Gate. For ten points, name this leader who restricted artistic subjects through his Cultural Revolution policies as the first Chairman of Communist China.",
      "answer": "Mao Zedong or Chairman Mao"
    },
    {
      "question": "These people benefited from a form of welfare known as the cura annonae. These people forced the creation of the Twelve Tables and gained a measure of equality after the Conflict of the Orders. They often lived in the subura neighborhood in tenements known as insulae. Their elected representative could not be harmed, as he was considered sacrosanct, and could convene their namesake council as a tribune. For ten points, name these ordinary citizens of Rome, often at odds with the upper class patricians.",
      "answer": "plebeians or the plebs"
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "To prevent complications in this process, the mTOR inhibitor rapamycin is used. Bruce Reitz and Thomas Starzl were innovators in this process, which Sir Roy Calne revolutionized by introducing ciclosporin, an immunosuppressant, to prevent rejection. Christiaan Barnard performed the first instance of this process involving the heart. For ten points, name this medical process in which another person’s living tissue surgically replaces a damaged or missing system.",
        "answer": [
          "organ transplant",
          "descriptive answers"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Rapamycin is named in honor of Rapa Nui, the native name of this island, where it was isolated in 1972.",
        "answer": "Easter Island"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "At an Iowa state fair, this man told a protester “corporations are people, my friend.” In November 2016, Donald Trump was photographed having dinner with this former “never Trump”er, who was hoping to be Trump’s pick for Secretary of State. Rick Perry called this man a “vulture capitalist,” attacking him for causing job losses while he led Bain Capital. A relatively popular health care reform bill was passed in 2006 while this man served as Governor of Massachusetts. For ten points, name this Republican politician, a Mormon who ran for President in 2012.",
        "answer": "Mitt Romney"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Mitt Romney refused to vote for either Donald Trump or Hillary Clinton in 2016; while we don’t know who he voted for, it’s entirely possible he voted for this Mormon candidate for president. This man received 21.5 percent of the vote in Utah and the fifth-most popular votes overall.",
        "answer": "Evan McMullin"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This group was legally given power by the Lex Titia and was formed after the Battle of Mutina. One of its members was forced out after raising a large force to defeat Sextus in Sicily. This group launched proscriptions against prominent politicians like Cicero. One member of this group divorced another’s sister to ally himself with Cleopatra. For ten points, name this political alliance of the late Roman Republic that failed to stop a civil war between two of its members, Octavian and Mark Antony.",
        "answer": "Second Triumvirate"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In addition to Octavian and Marc Antony, the Second Triumvirate included this aforementioned opponent of Sextus Pompey.",
        "answer": "Marcus Aemilius Lepidus"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Lawson Knott oversaw the certification of this constitutional amendment. Birch Bayh and Emmanuel Celler co-named a proposal to pass this amendment, which had added stipulations missing from the earlier Keating-Kefauver proposal; those stipulations included a process that resulted in the ascent of Nelson Rockefeller to his highest post in 1974. For ten points, name this amendment that clarifies Vice Presidential confirmation and allows for the President to temporarily give power to the VP in cases of disability.",
        "answer": "25th Amendment"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The 25th Amendment clarified, constitutionally what numerous laws had previously tried to establish;onesuchlaw,passedin1792,putthisCongressionalpositionfirstinlineaftertheVicePresident. As such, if Andrew Johnson had been successfully impeached, Benjamin Wade - then the holder of this position - would have taken office.",
        "answer": "President pro tempore of the Senate"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A novel by this author was probably inspired by the life of Enoch Crosby, a Revolutionary War era espionage agent whom he represented as Harvey Birch. A character created by this author, Judge Marmaduke Temple, gets rich by cheaply buying former Loyalist lands in the late 1700s. In a novel by this writer, Fort William Henry is surrendered to the French by Colonel Munro, whose daughter Cora is abducted by the Huron chief Magua. For ten points, name this author of The Spy, The Pioneers, and The Last of the Mohicans.",
        "answer": "James Fenimore Cooper"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Cooper also wrote a book about Alexander Slidell Mackenzie, who was court-marshaled after ordering the execution of three people for this crime. That incident involving this crime partially inspired Herman Melville’s novel Billy Budd.",
        "answer": "mutiny"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Claims that this man had been targeted by the Bulgarian secret service were investigated by the Mitrokhin Commission. During a visit to the Philippines, this man was targeted in the failed Bojinka plot; fourteen years earlier, this man survived an attack from a “Grey Wolf,” Mehmet Ali Agca [ah-jah]. This man, who encouraged the Solidarity movement in a 1979 speech in Warsaw, succeeded a similarly named pontiff who lasted only thirty three days in office. For ten points, name this Polish pope who was canonized in 2014.",
        "answer": "Pope Saint John Paul II or Karol J´ozef Wojtyla"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Another plot against Pope John Paul II took place in 1982 in this Portuguese parish, where three children saw a vision of Mary in 1917.",
        "answer": [
          "F´atima",
          "any elaboration that mentions F´atima and anything to do with the vision, including descriptions of Our Lady of F´atima"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In this battle’s opening stages, the Guadaloupe was scuttled to prevent capture. Lauzun’s Legion collided with a foraging party led by Banastre Tarleton during this battle. Thomas Graves’ fleet failed to join this battle because, earlier in the month, the Admiral de Grasse blocked him at Chesapeake Bay. The Comte de Rochambeau’s fleet ensured victory at this battle, where “The World Turned Upside Down” was allegedly played. For ten points, name this 1781 battle in which Cornwallis surrendered his British army to George Washington.",
        "answer": "Siege or Battle of Yorktown"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This major general accepted Cornwallis’ sword at the surrender ceremony, after Rochambeau and Washington turned down the gesture from Cornwallis’ assistant, Charles O’Hara.",
        "answer": "Benjamin Lincoln"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man helped end the Second Matabele [mat-ah-bay-lay] War by walking unarmed into an enemy base to negotiate; that base, Matobo Hills, later served as his burial grounds. This man’s greatest dream was described as a “red line” on a map. Though this man never fulfilled his vision of a “Cape to Cairo” railway, he managed to monopolize the diamond industry by founding De Beers. For ten points, name this Prime Minister of Cape Colony in South Africa, the namesake of a scholarship to study at Oxford.",
        "answer": "Cecil Rhodes"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Cecil Rhodes was forced to resign as Prime Minister of the Cape Colony after this raid into the South African Republic.",
        "answer": "Jameson Raid"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "Border Conflicts",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Statue built by Eiffel whose namesake island is owned by New York, but the surrounding waters owned by New Jersey.",
          "answer": "Statue of Liberty"
        },
        {
          "question": "River that, after much strife, became much of the border between the United States and Mexico.",
          "answer": [
            "Rio Grande",
            "Rio Bravo del Norte"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "South Dakota mountain range that is disputed with the Sioux Nation and home to Mount Rushmore.",
          "answer": "Black Hills"
        },
        {
          "question": "Border set by two surveyors in the 1760s, ending a dispute between Pennsylvania and Maryland.",
          "answer": "Mason-Dixon Line"
        },
        {
          "question": "Area past the Ohio river that British troops were forced to vacate after the signing of Jay’s Treaty.",
          "answer": "Northwest Territory"
        },
        {
          "question": "Conflict with Canada that was ended with the Webster-Ashburton Treaty.",
          "answer": [
            "Aroostook War",
            "Pork and Beans War"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Dispute over the San Juan islands which almost led to war with Britain after a certain animal was shot.",
          "answer": [
            "Pig War",
            "Northwestern Boundary Dispute"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "1839 war between Iowa and Missouri named for a substance found in three cut down trees.",
          "answer": "Honey War"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Margaret Thatcher",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Political party led by Thatcher against the Labour Party.",
          "answer": "Conservative and Unionist Party or Tory Party"
        },
        {
          "question": "War against Argentina that Thatcher orchestrated over an Atlantic island group.",
          "answer": "Falklands War"
        },
        {
          "question": "Method used by Thatcher to force an election in 1979. Passing this motion in Parliament forces the government to call a new election.",
          "answer": "vote/motion of no confidence"
        },
        {
          "question": "Industry that went on a failed strike in the winter of 1984 under the leadership of Arthur Scargill.",
          "answer": "coal mining"
        },
        {
          "question": "Good that Thatcher was accused of “snatching” from poor children as Education Secretary.",
          "answer": "milk"
        },
        {
          "question": "Chancellor of the Exchequer under Thatcher and her successor as Prime Minister.",
          "answer": "John Major"
        },
        {
          "question": "Assassination attempt by the IRA that Thatcher survived in October 1984.",
          "answer": "Brighton hotel bombing"
        },
        {
          "question": "Defence Secretary who challenged Thatcher for the leadership after the resignation of Geoffrey Howe.",
          "answer": "Michael Heseltine"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Military Theory",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Chinese general during the Spring and Autumn period who wrote the Art of War.",
          "answer": "Sun Tzu"
        },
        {
          "question": "French general who wrote the book Army of the Future before becoming leader of Free France.",
          "answer": "Charles de Gaulle"
        },
        {
          "question": "Chinese leader who wrote Protracted Warfare from his experiences fightning the Nationalists under Chiang Kai-Shek.",
          "answer": "Mao Zedong"
        },
        {
          "question": "Deterrence strategy based on the idea that a nuclear exchange would annihilate both attacker and defender.",
          "answer": "Mutually assured destruction or MAD"
        },
        {
          "question": "Admiral whose plan for a preventive strike was hurt by Admiral Nagumo’s decision to not send a third strike against Pearl Harbor.",
          "answer": "Isoroku Yamamoto"
        },
        {
          "question": "Author of The Influence of Sea Power Upon History, which explained Britain’s rise through its dominance of the sea.",
          "answer": "Alfred Thayer Mahan"
        },
        {
          "question": "Soviet military theory calling for attacks at the tactical front and throughout the battlefield to disrupt logistics and maintain a push.",
          "answer": [
            "deep battle or deep operation",
            "additional information"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "German general who wrote Achtung-Panzer!, the foundation of blitzkrieg.",
          "answer": "Heinz Guderian"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) These institutions are required by the Clery Act to publish statistics on crime that happens at or near them. These institutions cannot generally divulge records to the families of their customers, according to a law named (20 pts)",
        "FERPA; that law only applies to people 18 years or older. A pair of 2003 lawsuits against one of these institutions in Michigan forbade the use of quotas, but allowed them to use some forms of (10 pts)",
        "affirmative action. FAFSA is an application to receive federal aid for attending, for ten points, what institutions whose admissions offices are not federally required to look at SAT or ACT scores?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "colleges",
        "universitys"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This choreographer depicted the Spanish Civil War in Deep Song and homeless people during the Great Depression in “Steps In The Street,” part of a larger work. This choreographer of Chronicle frequently collaborated with the (20 pts)",
        "Japanese-American set designer and sculptor Isamu Noguchi. In another of this choreographer’s ballets, a newlywed Pennsylvania couple set up a (10 pts)",
        "farmstead to music that includes the Shaker hymn “Simple Gifts.” For ten points, name this modern dancer who choreographed Aaron Copland’s Appalachian Spring."
      ],
      "answer": "Martha Graham"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This empire secured power after defeating Marwan II at the river Zab. Chinese prisoners from the Battle of Talas aided this empire in establishing a paper mill at its capital, which had been moved from (20 pts)",
        "Damascus by Al-Mansur. The mathematician Al-Khwarizmi worked in this empire’s House of Wisdom, whose books allegedly turned the (10 pts)",
        "Tigris black from ink when Hulagu Khan sacked this caliphate’s capital at Baghdad. Harun al-Rashid ruled over, for ten points, what caliphate that succeeded the Umayyad dynasty?"
      ],
      "answer": "Abbasid caliphate"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In a propaganda poster published after this event, a woman with outstretched arms holds out a weapon underneath the caption “]Take Up the Sword of Justice.” Broadway producer Charles Frohman was a victim of this event, as was Alfred (20 pts)",
        "Vanderbilt, who was last seen trying to save a mother and child. Captain William Turner survived being swept overboard during this event, which occurred eleven miles off the (10 pts)",
        "Irish coast and took only 18 minutes. Walther Schwieger’s U-boat caused, for ten points, what 1915 sinking of a British liner, an act of war that helped push the United States into World War I? ANSWER:sinking oftheRMSLusitania(acceptanythingtodowithanattackontheRMSLusitania; prompt on partial answers) (5) The ZLB problem refers to situations where this quantity approaches zero. The difference between two rates of this quantity is measured by the TED spread by using LIBOR, a version of this quantity that was (+) fraudulently manipulated in London, and this value for the U.S. Treasury bond. This quantity approaches zero in a liquidity trap, a situation that the U.S. has employed (*) quantitative easing to try to avoid. In banking, an annual form of this quantity is described by the APR. For ten points, name this value which comes in simple and compound forms and represents the cost of borrowing money."
      ],
      "answer": "interest rate"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) One participant in this scandal tried to use it to avoid jail time for trying to steal Revolutionary War pensions. This scandal involved a series of letters with atrocious spelling errors but intelligent vocabulary; those letters were copied by the clerk John Beckley and were first published in a book by (20 pts)",
        "James Callender, who mistook this scandal for one of financial speculation. This scandal involved blackmail payments of several hundred dollars, then erupted with the 1797 publishing of a 95-page (10 pts)",
        "pamphlet announcing its author’s infidelity. For ten points, name this early American sex scandal that tarnished the political career of Alexander Hamilton."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Alexander Hamilton’s affair with Maria Reynolds",
        "anything mentioning Maria Reynolds, including the Reynolds pamphlet"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Description acceptable. This transaction involved Jacob Ruppert giving three promissory notes for $25,000 each, plus another $25,000 up front, plus a loan for $300,000 secured by a mortgage on a property at 4 Yawkey Way. Harry Frazee made this deal to cover his financial losses on (20 pts)",
        "musicals like My Lady Friends; four years later, Frazee’s No, No, Nanette was a smash hit. This transaction helped create the “Murderer’s Row” of (10 pts)",
        "1927 and led to an 86-year championship drought for the selling team. The “Curse of the Bambino” was triggered by, for ten points, what deal in which a legendary baseball slugger was sold by Boston to the Yankees?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "the sale of George Herman “Babe” Ruth from the Boston Red Sox to the New York Yankees",
        "equivalents for sale, including trade of Ruth even though it was just player for cash"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This speech expressed the hope that the U.N. could be a “true temple of peace” and not merely a “cockpit in a Tower of Babel.” The speaker noted that “the United States stands at this time at the pinnacle of world power” to an audience at (20 pts)",
        "Westminster College, Missouri in 1946. Alternatively called the Sinews of Peace, this speech claimed that, “from (10 pts)",
        "Stettin [...] to Trieste,” the title construct had “descended across the continent.” For ten points, name this speech by Winston Churchill that coined a term for the dividing line between Soviet and non-Soviet spheres."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Iron Curtain speech",
        "Sinews of Peace before mentioned"
      ]
    }
  ]
}